[[overview" role="wrapper">
== Overview
[[overview_logger">
=== Logging
		
			_Logging_
			is the process of writing log messages during the execution
			of a
			program to a central place. This logging allows you to
			report and
			persist error and warning messages as well as info
			messages (e.g.,
			runtime statistics) so that the messages can
			later be retrieved and
			analyzed.
		
		
			The object which performs the logging in applications
			is typically just called _Logger_.
		


[[overview_loggerjava">
=== Logging in Java
		
			Java contains the
			_Java Logging API_.
			This
			logging API allows you to
			configure which
			message types are
			written. Individual classes can use this logger to write messages to
			the configured log files.
		
		
			The
			`java.util.logging`
			package provides the logging
			capabilities
			via the
			`Logger`
			class.
		


[[overview_create">
=== Create a logger
		
			To create a logger in your Java code,
			you can use the
			following
			snippet.
		
		
			<programlisting language="java">
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/createLogger.java[]
----
		
		
			The
			`Logger`
			you create is actually a hierarchy of Loggers, and a `.` (dot) in the
			hierarchy indicates a level in the hierarchy. So if you get a Logger
			for the
			`com.example`
			key, this Logger is a child of the
			`com`
			Logger and the
			`com`
			Logger is child of the Logger for the empty `String`. You can
			configure
			the main logger and this affects all its children.
		


[[overview_level">
=== Level
		
			The log levels define the severity of a message. The
			`Level`
			class
			is used to define which messages should be written to
			the log.
		
		
			The following lists the Log Levels in descending order:
			
				
					*		SEVERE (highest)
		
					*		WARNING
		
					*		INFO
		
					*		CONFIG
		
					*		FINE
		
					*		FINER
		
					*		FINEST
		
				</itemizedlist>
			
		

		
			In addition to that you also have the levels
			<command>OFF</command>
			and
			<command>ALL</command>
			to turn the logging off or to log everything.
		
		
			For example, the following code sets the logger to the
			`info`
			level,
			which means all messages with severe, warning and info will
			be
			logged.
		

		
			<programlisting language="java">
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/setLogLevel.java[]
----
		


[[general_handler">
=== Handler
		Each logger can have access to several handlers.
		
			The handler receives the log message from the logger and
			exports
			it to a certain target.
		
		
			A handler can be turned off with the
			`setLevel(Level.OFF)`
			method
			and
			turned on
			with
			`setLevel()`
			method.
		
		
			You have several standard handlers.
			The following list gives
			some
			examples.
		
		
			
				*	
						ConsoleHandler: Write the log message to console
					
	
				*	
						FileHandler: Writes the log message to file
					
	
			</itemizedlist>
		
		
			Log levels
			<command>INFO</command>
			and higher will be automatically written to the console.
		


[[general_formatter">
=== Formatter
		
			Each handler's output can be configured with a formatter
		
		Available formatter
		
			*
					SimpleFormatter: Generate all messages as text
				

			*
					XMLFormatter: Generates XML output for the log
					messages
				

		</itemizedlist>
		
			You can also build your own formatter. The following is an
			example of a formatter which will create HTML output.
		
		
			<programlisting language="java">
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/MyHtmlFormatter.java[]
----
		


[[general_manager">
=== Log Manager
		
			The log manager is responsible for creating and managing the
			logger and the maintenance of the configuration.
		
		
			We could set the logging level for a package, or even a set
			of
			packages, by calling the
			`LogManager.setLevel(String name,
				Level level)
			`
			method. So, for example, we could set the
			logging level of all loggers
			to `Level.FINE` by
			making this call:
		
		
[source,text]
----
include::res/setLogLevel2.java[]
----
		


[[chapter20s1a">
=== Best Practices
		
			It is common practice to use the fully qualified name of
			each
			class whose activity is being logged as a message
			category, because
			this allows developers to fine-tune log
			settings for each class.
		
		
			Using the fully qualified class name of your class as the
			name of
			your Logger is the approach recommended by the
			Logging API
			documentation.
		


